Edgar!
What did he die of?
The same thing
our Church is going to die of.
Old age.
...et apostolicae fidei cultoribus.
What is it about that statuette
that you find so sensual?
I'd prefer not to delve into my psyche.
Holy Father, donations have declined.
Revenues from religious taxes
which our bishops and dioceses
depend on for their survival
have declined.
Tourist visits
to the Vatican have declined
greatly reducing the influx
of funds to Vatican City.
There is not much
that the Vatican Bank can do.
Our days of free willing
finances are over.
Changes in banking regulations
mean that our hands are now tied.
If we continue on this course
we'll be forced to start selling
off our artistic patrimony
simply to survive.
The faithful will return.
It's a natural cycle.
For now, the faithful
are not returning.
And small but dangerous enclaves
of Catholic fundamentalism
are starting to spring up,
just like in Islam.
Islam has more followers
than the Catholic Church.
Don't you find it a burden
to take on the responsibility
of such risky
and unpopular decisions?
No.
Your Holiness, who are you, really?
Pushing. Pushing, OK.
OK, Esther.
Push more.
Push.
Very good, Very good.
OK, Esther, OK, OK, OK.
Keep pushing, keep pushing now.
OK.
OK, OK.
♪ Kyrie Eleison
♪ Christe Eleison
♪ Pater Noster, qui es in Caelis
♪ Sanctificetur Nomen Tuum
♪ Adveniat Regnum Tuum
♪ Fiat voluntas Tua
♪ Sicut in Caelo, et in Terra
♪ Panem nostrum quotidianum
♪ Da nobis hodie
♪ Et dimitte nobis debita nostra
♪ Sicut et nos dimittimus
♪ Debitoribus nostris
♪ Et ne nos inducas in tentationem
♪ Sed libera nos a malo ♪
Flowers!
This is for the baby.
You shouldn't have, Holy Father.
It's a Bible that belonged to
Thomas Jefferson
the President of the United States
but it's like new,
he never opened it.
We certainly can't blame Jefferson,
the Bible isn't light reading.
We named him Pius.
A name for a bird.
He'll fly high!
Do you want to hold him,
Your Holiness?
That really would be
an unusual experience for me.
And for Peter and I
it would be an honor.
Pleasure to make your acquaintance,
Mr. Pius XIV.
It's a pity we can't remember
what we smelled like
when we were babies.
I do remember
what my parents smelled like.
He takes after you.
But if you look closely,
he also takes a little...
No.
He's a very good-looking baby.
He resembles his mother.
Holy Father.
Forgive me. I'm such a fool.
My hands only know
how to bless people.
It's all right Holy Father,
nothing happened.
I'm such an idiot.
We all have to get used
to new things, Holy Father.
Nothing happened.
Yes, yes you're right, Peter.
Valente, was there something you
wanted to tell me?
Holy Father, the Italian Prime Minister
is waiting for you in the Vatican.
Yes, of course,
it had slipped my mind.
Esther, I must go.
In my head,
I'll be at this audience
but in my heart
I'll never have left this room.
It's surprising to see
how a young woman
just moments after having a child,
can be transformed into a mother.
Are you asleep, Holy Father?
No, Mr. Prime Minister.
I'm praying for you
That's very thoughtful of you.
And thanks very much
for giving me this audience
after just nine months.
I didn't think you'd be running
the Country this long.
I said to myself: why bother?
But I was wrong.
Well...
how is this Italy of ours doing?
Much better, thanks to me.
You think so?
- Yes.
I think just the opposite.
You want it to do "much better"
perhaps you should keep firmly
in mind this list of requests.
I jotted it down in a hurry
just a few minutes ago.
If there's anything I've left off,
I can certainly add it to the list.
I'll make sure you receive
it promptly.
" Greater assistance
to Catholic families
no to common law marriages.
Mmm.
No to gay marriages
- Mmm.
more money to Catholic schools
further tax and banking benefits
to the Holy See.
Absolute prohibition
of abortion in all cases.
of divorce in all cases.
No to any temptation
to accept euthanasia
restrictions
on the religious freedom
of Muslims and Hindus.
Mmm.
A reopening of discussions
on the Lateran Pacts.
A full review of the territorial
boundaries of the Vatican State."
This last request really is
remarkable, I have to admit.
I didn't know that you had
expansionistic ambitions.
But I was told before coming that
this new Pope is a very funny man.
But did they forget to inform you
that this new Pope
was a man far more
intelligent than you?
No. Because it isn't true.
Do you know what the difference is
between me and you, Holy Father?
Let's hear.
The difference is that I was
elected with 41% of the votes.
That 41% exists.
You were elected by God.
And it's not a sure thing
that God exists.
Fine!
There's another element worthy
of your consideration:
just in case God
does happen to exist
do you know how long
it would take Him to wipe
that 41% off the face of the earth?
And where will God eradicate
that 41%?
At the polls in the next election?
Or in their homes
while they're watching TV?
Or perhaps in their sleep!
At the polls in the next election.
And what's more:
I, as the vicar of Christ
would be happy to help God
eradicate that 41%.
And if you don't stop playing the idiot
I'm gonna be forced to prove to you
that God does exist.
Let me explain something to you, Holy Father.
- Please.
Your demands might have
some basis in fact
at any other point in history.
At a point in history
when the Church was stronger
than it is right now
the Italian political equation
would have been obliged
to take your demands
under serious consideration.
The way it always has in the past.
But now
let us briefly analyze
your Papacy, Holy Father.
In the past nine months you have
never shown yourself
to the faithful.
You have not recited a single
Angelus in St. Peter's Square
you have not communicated
with anyone
you have simply retreated
into your palace on the hill
and you have threatened
and terrorized the faithful
through your terse
and telegraphic communiqués
in L'Osservatore Vaticano, with
obscurantist and retrograde theses.
The result has been that
according to a number
of highly respected studies
Italian Catholics have turned away
from the Church en masse.
This new development not only
allows me to ignore your requests
but it gives me
an even greater opportunity:
finally to modernize Italy.
Without fear of retaliation or the risk
of losing support among voters
I can review the colossal fraud
of the eight per thousand
Church tax
finally imposing punitive
taxes on the dioceses.
And, most important of all
I can finally free the country
from the pork barrels
stumbling blocks, and vetoes
of the Holy Roman Church
in the areas of euthanasia,
common law marriages
gay couples, abortion,
scientific research.
To cut a long story short,
Holy Father
thanks to you
I can start a revolution.
A very persuasive speech.
I'm glad we're finally beginning
to talk sense.
Persuasive and stupid
I might add, like every
politicians' speech.
And what's more, unrealizable.
Unrealizable?
- Hmm.
We shall see about that!
Now, if you'd care to listen to me
I'll show you that God exists
and how God and I can annihilate
that 41% of the population
that makes you feel so cheerful
and full of yourself.
I am very eager to hear what you
have to say, Holy Father.
I'm glad.
You see, Mr. Prime Minister
in the Sixties the young people
that protested in the streets
spouted all kind of heresies
all except one:
power to the imagination.
In that, they were correct.
The only problem was they had
no imagination.
And neither do you.
But God and I have plenty.
God and I are simply dripping
with imagination.
Now, just try and imagine
something with me:
Hmm?
- Hmm.
in six months, Italy will hold
the general election
and you will try to maintain
or increase
your 41% share of the electorate.
And right now everything indeed
points to your ability
to maintain that 41%.
Yeah.
But just imagine
a few weeks before the election,
there comes an announcement.
Pope Pius XIII has decided
to appear in public
for the very first time.
To talk to the Italian Catholics.
What morbid curiosity!
The whole world
is dying of curiosity.
And it is absolutely
to be expected
it's normal, we all want to see
that which is hidden
we all want to stare
the forbidden in the face.
Pius XIII appears and so
do his beautiful blue-eyes...
and this soft, round mouth.
A dazzling image
so dazzling it blinds people.
In other words, a powerful,
an evocative image
not unlike that of Christ.
But Pius XIII
doesn't merely dazzle
he offers reassurance as well.
With a magnificent speech,
full of quotations in Latin
it tells them that they,
the faithful, must not be afraid.
And why would they be afraid,
with a Pope as handsome
and reassuring as Christ?
Last of all, just a few short
weeks before the elections
the Pope says just two words:
"non expedit".
Do you know what that means?
- No.
No, of course you don't.
You're far too young.
The "non expedit" was first issued
by Pius IX in 1868.
It was eliminated by Benedict XV
in 1919
but guess what I can do?
What I, who am not answerable
to 41% of the Italians
but only to God who, by the way,
does not express His displeasure
on social network
if I make a mistake.
Guess what I can do?
I can restore the "non expedit".
The Catholics will all rush
to Google those words.
What do they mean?
The "non expedit" means
that the Holy Father
decrees it is unacceptable
for Catholics
to vote in the Italian elections.
And do you know what the surveys
that you have commissioned tell us?
They tell us that the number
of Italians who identify themselves
as Catholics are 87.8%
of the population.
Now you may say to me:
they could simply disobey you.
True.
But while a Catholic
might disobey the Pope
they'd never disobey Christ.
I'm already the former
but believe me, if I want to
I can have myself accredited
as the latter as well
and when I do,
you'll lose your election.
Here's how it works:
since you get 31% of your votes
from the Catholic electorate
you'd wind up with
a mere 10%.
I wouldn't be so sure
of those numbers, if I were you.
Mr. Prime Minister
take a look in this mirror.
What do you see?
Two young men.
One of whom is dressed
in a slightly odd style.
I, on the other hand,
see two media events.
One has already taken place,
that's you.
The other is about to happen.
Now, having set out
to prove to you
the existence of God
I believe I'm done.
But in that case, why...
why haven't you appeared
in public yet?
Because...
there's still no need.
Holy Father, would you like me
to see what I can do
to mend the relations
with the Italian Government?
- He's bluffing.
- Who?
The young man in a hurry
speaking on TV right now.
He's selling smoke and mirrors.
He won't do a thing he says.
Holy Father,
I've read the draft bills
that have already been approved
by the various commissions.
These people are deadly serious.
The revision of the eight
per thousand Church tax
would threaten the survival
of the Italian bishops.
Would that be such a bad thing?
What do we care?
You and I are the Holy See.
The Italian bishops
can take care of themselves.
Holy Father, I beg you,
this is no laughing matter.
Rest easy, he's bluffing.
Holy Father, believe me,
political awareness
is an archetypal emotion
for the Secretary of State.
Soccer mania is an archetypal
emotion for the Secretary of State.
I want to let you know that I've
been working hard on something new.
On what?
A measure forbidding priests
from giving absolution
in the confessional
to women who have had abortions.
Its a kind of soft,
disguised form of excommunication.
Holy Father, we will wake up
and find the women of the world
led by the Femen,
rushing the walls of the Vatican
hammers in hand,
bent on destruction.
Fine. We'll rebuild those walls,
taller and finer.
Old and unreliable Rorschach tests.
Orders to investigate intrusively
into the past of aspiring priests.
Young men paid bounties
to lure those aspiring priests
into compromising sexual situations
as soon as they're allowed
out into the world.
That's what I read in the directive
I found on my desk this morning
drawn up by who knows what renegade
underling while I was in Honduras.
Drawn up by me!
Every candidate for priesthood
takes a vow of chastity.
Their sexual predilections
are irrelevant.
Every candidate for priesthood
takes a vow of chastity
and none of them respect it.
That's the truth.
Well, I'm telling you no.
Lenny, I'm not okay with this.
I didn't go looking for my parents.
Instead, I went back to the orphanage,
in order to be with my friend
Andrew Dussolier
who was all I had left
in the world.
That was the beginning.
You owe me, as a friend,
and as a man of the cloth
who acknowledges my authority,
you must do what I ask.
♪ Do you know
♪ How sad it is to be a man alone
♪ I feel so
♪ solitary being in my home
♪ Without you
♪ I don't know what to do
♪ And I don't know where you are
♪ I can see
♪ My life is meant to
fall apart some day
♪ I got no girl
♪ So I got no world
♪ And I got no words left to say ♪
Here you are: Sanchez Angelo.
My superiors have determined
that you are neither suited for
nor worthy of the priesthood.
You are prohibited from requesting
admission to a seminary
in your home diocese
or in any other, for seven years.
Why?
Put in simpler terms,
the sexual disturbances afflicting you
are unacceptable
in terms of our standards.
What do you want?
Your resignation.
Otherwise...
our order will threaten a schism.
A schism?
Just try it.
I'll strip you of all you have.
Everything.
Your beds, your tunics,
your underpants
all those wonderful monasteries
you have in the most wonderful
loveliest places on earth.
Because all that belongs to me.
Are you ready to live on the streets?
Like St. Francis of Assisi?
Are you ready to sleep
on the ground
kicked and spat upon by junkies,
and homeless people, and drunks?
I'm ready to wage a war
without end against you.
Are you ready to wage that war
armed with nothing
but bottomless poverty?
I didn't think so.
And in that case,
stop talking bullshit
and get yourselves some shoes
because the air
in here is unbreathable.
Cardinal Dussolier
I know you,
but you don't know me.
I'm Contessa Emma Meraviglia,
the wife of General Meraviglia.
You know, I don't like seeing you
all on your own.
I'm accustomed to it, signora.
That's a bad custom to get into.
My girlfriends would compete
to keep you company.
And so would I.
In any case, my husband and I
will be hosting a party
Thursday at our villa.
If you're at loose ends,
please come.
It would be an honor
for my husband and me.
OK, thank you.
I'll keep it in mind.
Bye.
My name is Angelo Sanchez.
I was born in Alicante
into a family of manual laborers
and I am not a homosexual.
I had such a simple dream:
to serve God.
You murdered my dream.
You are nothing more
than a pathetic
miserable, cowardly murderer.
I could have been
an excellent priest.
Yeah, you could have.
I want to go home.
What do you mean, home?
We're both orphans.
You too?
- Me too.
I was abandoned by my parents
when I was just three years old.
Children are so lovely
when they are three years of age.
How can anyone abandon
a three year old?
Where do you find the nerve?
I never knew you were an orphan, too.
Well... now you know.
Does Lenny know?
- No.
And he never will.
Why not?
Because...
you don't steal
the stage from the Pope.
And you don't interfere
with his sorrow.